<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charity of church-men: or, A vindication of Mr William Walwyn merchant, from the aspersions plentifully cast upon him in a pamphlet, intituled, Walwyn's wiles. By H.B. Med. a friend to truth, his county and Mr Walwyn.</title>
            <author>Brooke, Humphrey, 1617-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4903A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E556_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205772</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865053</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865053</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117288</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117288)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E556[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charity of church-men: or, A vindication of Mr William Walwyn merchant, from the aspersions plentifully cast upon him in a pamphlet, intituled, Walwyn's wiles. By H.B. Med. a friend to truth, his county and Mr Walwyn.</title>
                  <author>Brooke, Humphrey, 1617-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hils, and are to be sold by W. Larnar, at the sign of the Blackmore, near Bishops-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIX. [1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>H.B. = Humphrey Brooke.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 28th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</term>
               <term>Walwins wiles.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117288:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARITY OF CHURCH-MEN: OR, A VINDICATION OF Mr <hi>William Walwyn</hi> Merchant, from the aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions plentifully caſt upon him in a Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>WALWYN'S WILES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>H. B.</hi> Med. a friend to Truth, his Country and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Walwyn.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 29.26.</bibl>
               <p>Many ſeek the Rulers favour, but every mans judgement commeth of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mark 3.6.</bibl>
               <p>And the Phariſees departed, and ſtraightway gathered a Councell with the Herodians againſt him, that they might deſtroy him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke 23.2.</bibl>
               <p>And they began to accuſe him, ſaying, we have found this man perverting the Nation.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Tim. 3.9.</bibl>
               <p>But they ſhall proceed no further, for their folly ſhall be manifeſt to all men, as theirs alſo was.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hils,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>W. Larnar,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Blackmore,</hi> near <hi>Biſhops-gate.</hi> M.DC.XLIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117288:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117288:2"/>
            <head>THE CHARITY OF CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH-MEN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He world cannot chooſe but take notice, of a ſtrangely malitious and ſcandalous Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>(Walwyn's Wiles, &amp;c.)</hi> the particular ſlanders whereof, though heretofore privately, yet induſtriouſly liſperſt, accompanied with many more of a lighter nature, but more eaſily diſcoverable, which are therefore in this book left out, yet have the pollitick Authors not thought fit to collect and publiſh the ſame, till they knew Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> was much ſtraitned from the means and opportunity of Vindicating himſelf; and till they judg'd by ſuch ſlanders, they ſhould render him odious to all Religious people, and ſo fit him for that deſtruction, they do ſecretly, but moſt laboriouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring upon him.</p>
            <p>He has been hitherto ſilent, and when importuned to clear himſelf; he has ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, <hi>That it was not the way of Chriſt or his Apoſtles; that we read of no Apologies of theirs, though in the ſame manner with himſelfe, but in a more plentifull meaſure loaded with obloquies and reproaches: That the beſt uſe he could make of ſuch hard ſpeeches, was to be more circumſpect in his waies, and not to deviate from the path of righteouſneſſe, that ſo by the innocence of his life, and unblamableneſſe of his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, he might give check to ſuch rumours and evil reports. That he knew very well what was the root from whence ſuch bitter fruits proceeded:</hi> viz. <hi>his engageing for the people, and diſcovering a reſolution in himſelf to perſevere in the ſame.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed neither he nor his friends did ever thinke they would have proceeded ſo far in theſe croſſe and rugged paths, as to proſecute him to the very death; for who could but ſuppoſe that either the precepts of Chriſtianity that are in direct oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to ſuch courſes, or at leaſt (if nothing elſe is prevalent with them) that the outward reputation of their Religion would have reſtrained them. But when once the innocent and harmeleſſe path is forſaken, whether then? but into a ſea of evil, where one bad action neceſſarily drawes on another; and one injuſtice enforces the committing of another, for ſupport and protection of the firſt? When Religious men become ſpies, and make uſe of friendſhip to betray; when they ſhall hunt their Brethren like Partriges, ranſack their whole lives, inſinuate themſelves into their acquaintance purpoſely to enſnare them, and juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſo doing: wreſt mens ſayings to the worſt, forge and fix upon them things of greateſt antipathy to their ſpirits; what is this but to blaſt the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and the profeſſion of Religion, and to make it evil ſpoken of all the world over? yet this hath been the practice of the Authors of that Pamphlet towards Mr. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> who has patiently bore all hitherto, and is now undergoing the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt proof of his vertue (which his Adverſaries make his crime and diſadvantage) and of his Chriſtian fortitude (with which I well know he is amply endowed) as in theſe latter times I thinke any man has undergon. They have ſeaſoned this project of theirs to the purpoſe; took a courſe for reſtraining him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and then they revile him; knowing well that other men, though of never ſo great acquaintance and intimacy with him, cannot ſo clearly diſcover the miſtakes and fallacious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of thoſe ſpeeches that are fathered upon him, as he himſelf could.</p>
            <p>However I judge my ſelfe bound to do my beſt (though weak) indeavour for his Vindication; out of my hearty reſpects to that Innocency and reall Goodneſſe that is ſo viſible in his life and converſation, as one would thinke ſhould anſwer all objections.</p>
            <p>Indeed I judge that Pamphlet more properly a deſigne, then a diſcourſe; the politick contrivance (moſt of it) of other kind of adverſaries then have ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117288:3"/>
their names to it, for that the end cannot be out of conſcience to prevent the perverſion of honeſt men; for then they would have publiſhed it when thoſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are pretended to be ſpoken; but to fit the people to bear his deſtruction patiently, and to make him (if poſſible) ſo odious as that they may cry out for it themſelves, and urge, as the deluded <hi>Jews</hi> did againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> away with him, 'tis not fit ſuch a man ſhould live upon the Earth.</p>
            <p>And that which the more confirmes me therein is, becauſe one maine drift of the book is to take off the People from complaining of their Burdens and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and rendring all them as ſuſpitious of ſome dangerous deſigne, that ſhall give advice for the doing thereof; fixing an evil ſence upon all the motions of theirs to that end, eſpecially upon ſuch as give them Councel, or are moſt able amongſt them, to thinke of wayes and means for getting relief, or deliverance. Now becauſe Mr. <hi>Walwyn</hi> has been alwayes a ready friend to all ſorts of people uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuffering in any kind; and is ſtil putting ſuch as are in Authority in remembrance of their duty, and has been a moſt unwearied ſolicitour theſe 8. years, for the juſt rights and liberties of People: hence is it that as heretofore he was made the marke of bad mens diſpleaſure: ſo even now, when we hope to ſee better times, is become the common Butt againſt which all harſh cenſures are directed; and all this to over-awe mens ſpirits, and, by frighting him and others from doing their duties, make them ſubmit to any yoaks that ſhall be brought upon them.</p>
            <p>Henceforward to Petition will be rendred a matter dangerous to the State, and he that ſhall ſet himſelf to frame and manage ſuch things, may in like manner as Mr. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> be ſaid to inſinuate into, and miſlead the people; to ſtudy their tempers and complexions, the qualifications of their ſpirits, their humours and paſſionate inclinatioins, their externall quality and eſtate, purpoſely to deceive them: he that ſhall urge the preſſures and exceſſive burthens we groane under, and inſiſt upon the cauſes and remedies thereof, muſt by this way of judging, be a ſeditious perſon, an incenſer of the people againſt Authority; a politick perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of man-kind, which is ſuch a machiavilian way of ſtopping our mouthes and making us ſtoop under every yoak that may be laid upon us, as no ſort of men hitherto arriv'd unto.</p>
            <p>'Tis well the Author of that Pamphlet and his accomplices are ſo wel pleaſed with the preſent ſad and deplorable condition of the Common wealth: the world goes wel with them it ſeems, ſo they enjoy the eare and favour of Authority; and have faire hopes of advancing ſuch of themſelves as are not already advanc'd into places of profit; what care they though the poor ſtarve, though all kinds of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion be trebled and ten-coupled upon the Common-wealth: the fiſh is caught and therefore away with the nets, there muſt be Tyranny (ſo they now argue) and why not in theſe rather then in any elſe? changings are dangerous, and in time all that is deſirable ſhall be eſtabliſhed; and therefore let us as it becomes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, waite with patience upon Authority and ſee what they will doe: Thus they perſwade moſt to a yeilding contentfull ſubmiſſion to the yoak, who once taken off, are ingaged for juſtification of themſelves, to plead and argue againſt thoſe who ſee through the ſubtiltie of ſuch deceptions, and continue notwithſtanding all hazards, watchful and induſtrious as wel to manifeſt and bring to light what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooful, as to diſcover what is pernitious to their Country.</p>
            <p>'Gainſt ſuch as theſe, what means more effectuall then ſcandals? and what ſcandals more odious then Atheiſm and Communitie? By the firſt, all that are religious are incens'd, by the luſt of all that are rich. And though the whole progreſſe of Mr <hi>Walwyns</hi> life and converſation doth clearly evince the falſe imputation both of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117288:3"/>
one and the other; yet having happily ſcattered in familiar diſcourſes, ſome words, that by the extremity of wreſting and miſ-application, for want of obſervation of the coherence, by taking a piece only, or part of his ſpeech; all which, ſuch as came purpoſely to betray, muſt needs be ſuppoſed to be very much inclin'd unto; 'tis no wonder, if in ſo many years watching and way-laying him, ſome words be not gathered, which in a perverted ſenſe may look that way.</p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Saviour, notwithſtanding the Divinity of his Nature, was frequently ſo miſ apprehended; and though his deſign in this world was only to do good, and die for mankind; yet was he rendred by the policies of the Jews, a Subverter of the Law, an enemy to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ceſar:</hi> When a liberty ſhall be taken to ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny and comment upon other mens lines, and to judge of their ends and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what man of parts and buſineſſe in the world, but may be rendred odious? Who is there but may have ſuch a gloſſe put upon his actions, as to make him appear a man of wicked deſigns? 'Tis a courſe, indeed, that if we ſhould retaliate in the like kind, would in time heighten us to the extremeſt acts of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence one towards another, and beget everlaſting feuds and enmity amongſt us. If they ſuppoſe we want matter; we anſwer, that 'tis not good for them to truſt to it, for we have a Bedrole of ſuch enormities in ſome of the chief of them, that had we not great reſpects to peace, and reluctancy within us to diſcover the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of other men, we could make them aſhamed of themſelves: But ſuppoſe we did want matter, we anſwer, ſo alſo do they; and we, as well as they, may make it, and no leſſe plauſibly: If we would take upon us to judge Mr <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> might we not ſay, he is a Time-ſerver, and viſibly ſo? That his Doctrines are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory, not framed by the Line of Truth, but the probability of ſucceſſe in each Party? That therfore when there was hopes of the Kings Reſtauration, he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued him to be unaccountable to any earthly Tribunall, and, as the conſecrated corn, to be cut only by the hand of God: That he abhorred both the Jeſuiticall Doctrine and Practice of taking away Kings; and yet afterwards, when the hopes of his return was over, and that he knew not only the proſecution of his Perſon, but alſo an abolition of the Kingly Office intended; who then became a more ſtout Arguer for the ſame then he? And though theſe things in a candid ſenſe may be ſaid to proceed from a further dicuſſion and conſideration of the point, and the appearance of light in him, yet allowing every man the liberty that the Author of the Pamphlet takes: how eaſie is it to fix ſuch a cenſure upon him?</p>
            <p>So in like manner Mr <hi>Goodwin</hi> having ſaid, That no Tranſlation of the Bible, nor yet no Copy in the Originall Languages, can be truly called the Word of God: how clearly does it follow, that then we have no Word of God amongſt us, ſince we have nothing that can in any ſenſe be called Gods Word, but either the Copies or Tranſlations, the Originall being kept from us? Neither doth he, when he comes to explain himſelf, much mend the matter, ſince the ſpirituall ſenſe, and Divine interpretation, which only in his judgment deſerves the name of Gods Word, is divers in every man; and that opinion the way to make our apprehenſions the the Judge of the Scriptures, and not the Scriptures the rule of our apprehenſions. Hereupon, if, as the Author of the Pamphlet, a man may take liberty to aſſert, that when thoſe things were ſpoken, it was Mr <hi>J. Goodwins</hi> intention, to ſubvert the very Foundations of other Divines, and of the Scriptures themſelves, becauſe the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience was then denied him; how obvious would the inference be? And though he hath ſince evinced the Divine Authority of the Scriptures in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yet ſince Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> hath done the like, and never ſaid ſo much, nor ſo clearly to the contrary: what reaſon is there, but that he may ſtand as fair in the opinion of mankind, as Mr <hi>John Goodwin</hi> in that point?</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117288:4"/>
            <p>For the ſcandalous ſpeeches that in the Book are Father'd upon Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> though I cannot expreſly and circumſtantially manifeſt, that they are all falſe and forged, yet for the chief of them, which are of the fouleſt ſavour, I ſhall: For the reſt, I ſhall either paſſe them over, and leave them to Mr <hi>Walwyn's</hi> own confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; or from my knowledge of his oppoſite judgment in the particulars, evince the improbability of his ever ſpeaking them.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, 'tis thus far true, That Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> and a Member of Mr <hi>Goodwin's</hi> Congregation, together with my ſelf, did upon a Faſt day (as it hath been the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall manner of many of his Members) (an eie witneſſe may ſpeak it, and as Mr <hi>John Price's</hi> Pulpit Incendiary doth abundantly evidence) go to hear Mr <hi>Cranford,</hi> and ſome others, it being the time when the conteſts about Conformity and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration were very high: 'Tis likewiſe true, that we did all agree, comming after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards home to Mr <hi>Walwyns,</hi> that the Miniſters did ſeverally ſpend their time either upon uſeleſſe ſubjects, ſuch as did little tend to edification; or about advancing their own intereſts and reputation with the people; and that Gentleman was as forward in ſuch expreſſions as we. 'Tis true, that <hi>Lucian</hi> was taken off a ſhelf ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by me, or Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> I can't ſay which, and that we read one of his Dialogues, which was the Tyrant, or Megapenthes; and afterwards commended it as very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the time he lived; when by ſetting forth the foulneſſe and deformity of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie in a third perſon, he informed the people of the wickedneſſe of ſuch under whom they lived: but that any compariſon was made between that and the Bible, is as falſe as in it ſelf ridiculous.</p>
            <p>'Tis at leaſt 4 or 5 years that the Gentleman hath charg'd his memory with this; in all which time, his hatred and enmity againſt Mr <hi>VValwyn</hi> being in its growth, (for he is of the Councel and Faction) 'tis no wonder if he be biaſs'd thereby to find that which he came purpoſely to look for, whether it were really there, or no.</p>
            <p>Beſides, Mr <hi>VValwyn</hi> prefer'd <hi>Lucian</hi> (as the Pamphlet ſaies) for wit, before the Bible: 'Tis well known, that Mr <hi>VValwyn</hi> hath the loweſt eſteem of wit that may be, counting it the lighteſt, volatile and ſuperficiall part of a man; whence his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation is, that commonly thoſe that have moſt wit, have moſt wickedneſſe: He diſtinguiſhes between Wit and Wiſdom, and prizes only the latter, as of reall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoof and benefit to mankind; it being that, which through the concomitant bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Almighty, bears a man through all the ſtraits and exigencies of this life: whereas Wit is but the exuberance of light and unſteady minds; which ſince he in all other matters diſlikes; for the truth whereof, I appeal to all that know him: What ground is there for the leaſt ſuppoſall that he ſhould for that prefer <hi>Lucian</hi> before the Bible?</p>
            <p>For his opinion concerning Hell, 'tis clearly thus: Though he judges every wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man to have, <hi>intus Gehennam,</hi> a Hell in his own Conſcience; as on the contrary, every good man to have the Kingdom of God within him; yet upon ſtrict ſearch, which we to-gether have made into the Scripture, we have concluded, that there is another Hel ſucceeding judgment, convinced by thoſe places of Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. 2 <hi>Theſſ. c.</hi> 1. So that the miſtake is, that becauſe he ſaid, there is a Hel within man, therfore he concludes, there's none without him: And though it ſeems contrary to reaſon, that a man ſhould be puniſhed everlaſtingly for a little ſinning in this world, in which ſenſe only he ſpoke it: yet have we both ſubmitted our Reaſons to Gods Word, the places fore mentioned being expreſſe for the ſame.</p>
            <p>For Books of Morality and Hiſtory, though Mr <hi>VValwyn</hi> gives them their doe eſteem, and judges that the peoples reading them would very much advance their knowledge, and enable them to preſerve themſelves in freedom, by ſeeing through
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117288:4"/>
the policies of bad men and their many ſleights by which they abuſe and enſlave the people, which are plentifully deſcribed in thoſe Books: And thus far the Author ſpeaks truth of him. Yet hath Mr <hi>VValwyn</hi> never elevated them beyond their proper ſphere, or deſert, nor made compariſons between them, and that Book which he ever hath accounted, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Book of Books,</hi> and truly deſerving the name of Bible, or the Book, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon to which, all others, though good and uſefull in themſelves, do not yet deſerve any eſteem: This I do as truly know to be his judgment in this particular, as I know 'tis day when the Sun ſhines amongſt us.</p>
            <p>That he hath blamed the ſimple practice of this Nation, in bringing up their Children to learn Latin and Originall Languages, is moſt falſe; but that he hath and doth condemn the tedious and tireſome way that is taken in doing the ſame, is moſt true; his judgment in this particular being, that Children may be taught Latin, Greek and Hebrew, in a fourth part of the time that is now ſpent therein, and that purpoſely for the gain of the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter.</p>
            <p>It is as true, that he diſlikes in the education of Children, that the Languages only are propoſed, and not the principles of Divinity, and the precepts of Morality, in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as that their underſtandings may be poſſeſſed therewith, whereby they may be made both religious and true Common-wealths-men. And that alſo ſome Art, Mechanick or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture, be taught according as their genius and diſpoſition of body ſhall encline them; that ſo they may be both able to provide for themſelves, and ſerviceable to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>How eaſie in theſe particulars it is for other men to miſtake him, that continually lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the catch, and are ready to interpret every thing he ſpeaks to the worſt, let the world judge. And conſider likewiſe, how exceedingly it doth miſ-become thoſe that profeſſe Chriſtianity, eſpecially a more pure and refined way then other men, to lie lurking privily to deſtroy the innocent. That the Scribes, Phariſees and Lawyers ſhould aſk queſtions, and inſinuate themſelves into good mens company to betray them, is no wonder: but that it ſhould be done, and profeſſedly done by ſuch as would be thought of a near relation to God, ſuch as ſeparate from others becauſe they will not have a profane perſon among them, doth to my underſtanding call in queſtion the ſincerity of their aſſembling, and import the end thereof to be, not the edification one of another, but the undermining of all other men and waies, that are in any oppoſition to them. I ſpeak not this of the generality of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who queſtionleſſe have good and Religious ends in congregating together; but of that Veſtry or Conclave of them, that ſit as Judges of every mans fame and reputation, and have for that purpoſe their Emiſſaries to bring them in matter to raiſe Batteries againſt any mans good name, they would make hatefull: They have indeed too exactly learn'd <hi>Machiavel's</hi> rule, to ſpare not to ſcandalize and traduce their adverſaries; for that though ſome of the dirt may be wiped off, yet part of it will ſtick, and they ſhall be ſure not altogether to loſe their labours.</p>
            <p>Where by the way, let every good man conſider, whether their mixing with other men, under the notion of Friends, their getting into familiar acquaintance, eating and drinking together, and all this to betray, be not like <hi>Judas,</hi> kiſſing our Saviour, and in effect the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving of all ſociety and friendſhip: For how ſhould I, or any man know, but that every man, though ſeemingly a boſome Friend, is indeed a Traitor? How can this chooſe but take away the ſweetneſſe of friendſhip, and make us every one jealous one of another? Seriouſly I think they could not have done an action ſo diſcordant to Religion, nor of ſo evil conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to mankind.</p>
            <p>For the Objection in the generall, That Mr <hi>VValwyn</hi> labours, and makes it his main buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to bring people out of love with Religion and the Scriptures, is a thing in it ſelf ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, as I think nothing can be more; For what can be the end of a man in doing ſo? And
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117288:5"/>
certainly every wiſe mans actions are directed to ſome end: What would mens Athe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> advantage him, ſince 'tis clear as day, and all his endeavours manifeſt it, that he ſtrives to have every man good And ſince he knows, that Religion doth reſtrain men from committing thoſe evils, that otherwiſe they would ruſh u, on, were that neceſſary Tie of Conſcience ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off. Beſides, I profeſſe as in the preſence of Almighty God, that I know no man that endeavours with more exactneſſe to ſquare his life according to the Rule Scripture, then Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> doth; which is the cleareſt argument in the world, that they are dear and precious in his eies; and all thoſe I know, that are obſervers of his life and converſation, will give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony thereunto.</p>
            <p>The true ground of this bitterneſſe of ſpirit againſt him may well be ſuppoſed to be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot aſſociate into a Church way, upon their grounds; as not knowing any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be ſo quallified as Miniſters of the Goſpel ought to be; which he thinks is eſſentiall to ſuch an aſſociation, and is in expectance that in time it will be ſo. In the mean time, he approves Congregationall Aſſemblyes for inſtructing the people, and for the conſideration and right underſtanding of the Scriptures; as alſo, for the making every man in love with true piety and virtue, and to loath whatſoever is evil: But becauſe he can no more approve the Divine Authority and Saintſhip of the Independent Paſtours then of others before them; and reckons, that they are ſuch but in pretence and ſhew only, and is eſteemed able to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and evince the ſame: Hence have they drawn out their ſharpeſt arrows, even bitter words, and let them fly at him, hoping thereby to make invalid whatſoever he ſhall ſay in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>And this indeed, appears to be the true ground of their perſecuting him, and making uſe of all means, direct or indirect, to blaſt his ſpotleſſe reputation, and which hath made them gather up that heap of forgeries and calumnies which in that Book are contained.</p>
            <p>For theſe ſpeeches which are ſaid to be other mens whom he hath perverted; although I very much queſtion, whether they were ever ſpoken by any man, they are ſo abominably profane and wicked: yet 'tis moſt clear, that for Mr <hi>John Price,</hi> or whoever is the Author of the Pamphlet, to ſuggeſt that which he cannot know, namely, that ſuch wicked ſpeeches have proceeded from the mans acquaintance with Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> doth clearly diſcover the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſneſſe of his heart, and the Un-Chriſtian ſpirit that is within him: which indeed is more evident by theſe bitter expreſſions that are ſcattered through his Book, as, Engliſh man Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Factor for the Devil, Cunning and Hypocriticall Jugler, Wretched man, Journey-man, and Apprentice to the Prince of darkneſſe, Artificiall and great Impoſter, &amp;c. all which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from within him, do clearly manifeſt the defilements of his ſoul, and from what ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour all the reſt hath proceeded.</p>
            <p>But the height of his bitterneſſe is diſcovered in a ſtory concerning a Gentlewoman, whom he is ſaid in her great paine and diſtemper to adviſe to make away with her ſelfe: a thing ſo falſe and ſcandalous, as I know not what can be more; For Mr. <hi>VValwyn</hi> hearing of her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, and melancholly reſolutions, did out of the reſpects he bore unto her (being a Woman of ſo much goodneſſe, and with whom and her huſband, he had been of long inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate acquaintance) frequenty viſit her, and adviſed me to do the like purpoſely to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie her ſpirit againſt ſo harſh and ſinful a reſolve, which we both did; and as her huſband knowes to good purpoſe, that ſhe was often much more chearful and better diſpos'd after our being with her then at other times: Inſomuch that he has often deſired both Mr. <hi>VVal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyns</hi> and my frequent viſitation of her. For a fuller teſtimony thereof, I intended that the Gentleman himſelf ſhould have atteſted ſo much: but he being very ſick in the Country, and his Siſter and ſervants urging to me the danger of bringing to his remembrance his Wives ſad diſaſter, and telling me, that probably it might be his ſudden death, I have forborn for a time, till God ſhall give him more ſtrength and health.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> hath been often with him ſince his Wives death, and been as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117288:5"/>
fairly accepted as ever (as his Son and ſervants know) What cleerer Argument can there be, but that he does acquit M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> of any ſuch horrid action, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading his wife to make away with her ſelf?</p>
            <p>Beſides, if M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> had bin ſo wicked as to urge her, can he be ſuppoſed to do it before I know not what ſtranger that told them the buſineſs; when the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-woman that was alwaies with her, her Siſters and ſervants, do none of them know any thing of the buſineſs, but are ready to atteſt his frequent perſwading her to the contrary.</p>
            <p>By the falſhood of this particular ſlander, a man may gueſs at the truth of all the reſt; for they that will be ſo forward to divulge a Forgery ſo exceedingly tending to the diſcredit of another, and make expoſtulations thereupon, and appeals as the People; adviſing them to judge of the Frame, Temper, and Spirit of the man by this action; where will they ſtick? Or what will they not do to take away his life, which when a mans good name is gone is not at all to be valued? For a good Name, what is it, but the life of a mans life? I am very ſorry for Religions ſake, which I fear will very much ſuffer by this demeanor of men, whom I wiſh I could alwaies have accounted Religious. But I ſee, it is not an habit of Speaking, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Study and Cuſtom, nor an Ability to Diſpute or Diſcuſs a point in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, that truly denominates a man ſuch; but the inward ſweetneſs and calmneſs of Spirit, that Chriſtianity preſcribes; and which indeed, is more eminent in M. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> then I have known it in any man; whoſe way hath alwaies bin, to take the injur'd mans part, to diminiſh the aggravations of an accuſer, ſlowly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly to hear any thing that tends to the preiudice or diſ-repute of another: as knowing well the aptneſs and propenſion in moſt men, to give credence when they hear o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers ill ſpoken of. I cannot chuſe but upon occaſion break out into theſe Speeches concerning M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> (and I queſtion not but good men will excuſe me for it) becauſe I am ſo experimentally ſenſible of the Truth thereof: Indeed, if I were to chuſe a true Friend, a vertuous and Religious Aſſociate, addicted to no vice or extravagancy, the moſt averſe from contention, the moſt cheerful and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant (but for the diſturbance of his Spirit to ſee the Common-wealth ſtill in ſo ſad a condition) If I would chuſe a man to be readily aſſiſtant to his power in any diſtreſs, and that makes Conſcience of his duty to God and man: It ſhould be M. <hi>Walwyn:</hi> And <hi>I</hi> heartily bleſs God, that he hath afforded me the enjoyment of his Society for theſe eight yeers together, and upward; which I do reckon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the prime bleſſings of this life, and which I would not utterly leave, for any worldly Temptation whatſoever. God knows, I flatter not, for what need have I to flatter? but ſpeak the truth of my heart, being inwardly conſcious both of his innocence and goodneſs, of the many preſſures that undeſervedly ly upon him; out of which I hope God almighty will ſhortly free him, by cleering all Scruple, and falſe Apprehenſions concerning him. But to proceed.</p>
            <p>What M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> has ſaid concerning Profeſſors, I know not; but ſure there is much to be ſaid, and much in them to be amended; haply in this particular he has bin more earneſt than ordinary; becauſe he ſees ſo large a diſproportion between the Rule and their Practiſe: and ſince this is true and acknowledged ſo by the Author, how uncharitable muſt he needs appear, in judging M. <hi>Walwyns</hi> urging the ſame, to proceed from a deſigne to diſparage Religion, and the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors thereof? Sure I am, that if any man could be ſo wicked as to propoſe ſuch a deſigne to himſelf, as the diſparagement of Religion and its Profeſſors, he would
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117288:6"/>
not check, but countenance their wickedneſs; then which, nothing can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſcreditable to Religion.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Walwyns</hi> next drift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſaid to be, to procure the trouble, miſery, and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of this Common-wealth: A goodly work indeed, and which is likely, that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which hath ſpent himſelf for the Parliament, and in endeavouring a good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſettlement of the Common-wealth, ſhould ever admit into his thoughts. For what end ſhould he attempt any ſu h thing? If for wealth or greatneſs, was an improbable way is that to get e ther? Beſides, he has hitherto bin regardleſs of both: and certainly, if they had bin his end, he has brain and ability enough to have compaſſed them both, by ſtriking in with any party that has had the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation thereof. But in this the calumniation of M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> is not ſo principally intended, as to ſtartle the people from finding fault with any thing that is aunſwer from complaining of the failings and undue management of things, by ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or may be in Authority; for this he cries out upon, as the means to carry on his private deſigne, which will queſtionleſs, be extended to any who ſit not down contented with whatſoever happens, but appear in never ſo moderate deſires for the rectification of what is amiſs. How has he by this means, fitted every man with a way how to find fault with Petitioners; to ſtilo them of <hi>Walwyns</hi> gang, deceived by his Wiles and Impoſtures; and ſo to take away that laſt human Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge which good men have left them, <hi>viz.</hi> of making their Grievances known, and deſiring Redreſs? For the waies which he is ſaid to uſe to ſeduce the poor and indigent, is by telling them that vertue and ability for diſcharge of a Publike truſt, ought to be the characteriſtical tokens of fitneſs to bear Office, and places of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and that it is a moſt unfiting thing that one man ſhould have thouſands to ſpend upon his luſts, and another want neceſſaries; though neither of theſe I think have ſo much irrationality or unchriſtianity in them, as to deſerve to be cryed down by a Member of a Church, and are as uncharitably urged as ſuppoſed weapons M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> fights withal, in order to an imagined deſign, their either weak or wicked thoughts have invented. Yet can I truly ſay of M. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> as from my own knowledge, that he hath ever proteſt and propoſed not to ſupply poor men by injuring the Rich, but by reducing the Common-wealth to ſo good a paſs, that every man by care and eaſie labour, might have wherewithal to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf and his Family in ſome comfortable manner.</p>
            <p>To take away from any man what is his by inheritance, or by his trade or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, or any other way, is ſo viſibly contrary to the equity which he hath ever (according to his underſtanding) held forth, not onely in the front, but in the very heart of his deſignes (or what you pleaſe to call them) which makes me think that book was compiled by ſome-body that knows him not, but has had a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p of matter at random, gathered up and given him by ſuch as knew him able to make inferences, and contrive a ſubtle Pamphlet thereupon; not onely to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate M. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> but to ſtop the mouth, of all the aggrieved and diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people of the land, and for that end has he marſhall'd all the ſeveral oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and burdens of the Common-wealth, into ſeveral ranks; as if they were not real things, but inventions of M. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> to irritate by ſome of them, the poor; by others, the rich; by ſome, the raſh and cholerick; by others, the diſcreet and apprehenſive; to diſcontent and diſ-affection againſt ſuch as are in Authority. So that queſtionleſs they hope by this means to terrifie all now from opening their mouths, be they under what oppreſſion ſoever; though for my part, I think it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117288:6"/>
will work a contrary effect, when men ſhall ſee the Arts and Stratagems that are uſed to make them ſtoop under their burdens <hi>Iſſachar</hi>-like; and that the private Church-men are become the Sluggards of their fair and lawful endeavors, to redeem themſelves from thoſe preſſures that ly upon them.</p>
            <p>Did not in like manner the King and Biſhops make the Scots odious, and the Puritan Party in England, a by-word, urging ſuch like ſlanders of them, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it was the deſigne of ſome diſcontented ſpirits, to alienate mens affections from their Governors, and that by private diſcourſes, by printing and publiſh ng Books, ſending into ſeveral Counties, and ſlinging them into mens houſes, as this Author impoſeth upon Mr <hi>Walwin?</hi> Nay, did not the Presbyter Party, in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Mr <hi>Edwards,</hi> Mr <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and others, do the like upon the Independents, Sectaries, Seekers, &amp;c. inventing ſtrange Deſigns, like theſe father'd upon Mr <hi>VValwin,</hi> and caſting them upon any that they had a mind to make odious? And did not Mr <hi>Goodwin</hi> himſelf bear an ample ſhare of theſe Calumnies, being ſtiled by them, <hi>The Grand Heretick of England, a plucker up (preſumptuouſly) of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Priviledges of Parliament by the roots:</hi> and is not this work of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor the very ſame in effect, manner, and deſign? the tide being now turn'd, and the ſtream of profit runing into a new Channel; the only difference being a more ſubtile contrivance in this pageant of ſcandals, then hath yet by any of them been produced.</p>
            <p>It will be needleſs for me to run over more particulars, the Principal having been already cleered, and the Remainder being but of the ſame batch and leven with the other; and if true, as in the rankneſs of their expreſſion they are not, they cannot beget that abomination againſt him, which they expect.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Ware</hi> buſineſs, it is ſo baſe and abominable a Fiction, ſo apparently the wicked ofſpring of a Politick brain, that little needs to be ſaid to it, only thus, That if there had been any ſuch deſign of the Agitators at <hi>Ware</hi> of the Outing the Lord General, deſtroying the Lievt. General, and forcing the Parliament to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the King, and Mr <hi>Walwin</hi> privie to it; the whole town ſhould certainly have rung of it before now, and not only ſo, but the Deſigners ſhould have been proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for it, ſince there is Law ſufficient for that; (Civil Law I mean, without the help of Martial) and ſince neither Power nor Authority hath been wanting to ſee ſo plain a piece of Iuſtice executed; what therefore doth the not doing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of more cleerly argue, then the preſent forgery of this preſent fable, for their friend Mr <hi>Walwins</hi> ſake, whoſe ſpotleſs innocence leaves them without any ground to raiſe their batteries againſt him, but with what comes out of the Mint of their own inventions.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Author ſaies not that Mr <hi>Walwin</hi> was of, or privie to that Deſign, but only layes it upon certain Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tators at <hi>Ware;</hi> and yet he craftily and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly inſerts it amongſt other things he hath fram'd and father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon Mr <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> of purpoſe to make the world believe that this is alſo his.</p>
            <p>If People knew how fertile their brains have been with Fictions of this nature, they would ſay all were not Chriſtians that took that name upon them, and ſeem'd ſo zealous for the honor of God and dignity of the Scriptures: There is indeed ſcarce any thing that concerns a mans life, but Mr <hi>Walwin</hi> hath been abuſed in, by ſoul Reports: to ſome he is ſaid to <hi>parat his face,</hi> having heen hitherto of a ruddy complexion; and the Reporters have been tric'd from one to another, till one would go no further, but only told him, That he heard it of credible men.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117288:7"/>
            <p>Others report him looſe in his Life, and one Mr <hi>Woollaſtone</hi> meeting M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cobet,</hi> bid him beware of Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> for he was a dangerous man, a Ieſuite, as Anti-ſcripturiſts; and to make the laſt good, ſaid, That a Woman being tempted by him to lewd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs, ſhe reply<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng that it was againſt Gods Word which ſaies, <hi>that Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge:</hi> Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> (as this bade man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported) made anſwer, <hi>What telſt thou me of that idle Book?</hi> Whereupon Major <hi>Cobet</hi> told Mr <hi>Woollaſtone</hi> that he would tell Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> of this, and that he ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k to be called to an account for it: Within a while after, a Meeting being at the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndmill in <hi>Lothbury</hi> about a Petition, Major <hi>Cobet</hi> told Mr <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyn</hi> of it before ſix or ſeven other men, at which M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> wondered he ſhould be ſo abuſed, having no other way left to cleer himſelf but by a denyal and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the thing: But it ſo fell out, that imediatly after Mr <hi>Woollaſtone</hi> came into the Room, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng urged by Major <hi>Cobet</hi> to make good what he had reported to him concerning Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> before thoſe ſix that were preſent; Mr <hi>Woollaſton</hi> Anſwered, <hi>That he confeſt he had injured Mr</hi> Walwyn <hi>in the Report, and deſired his Pardon, for the words were true of another, but not of him:</hi> In Witneſs of the truth of what is here Related I Subſcribe my name.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng all which, both this and other ſcandals of the like nature are ſtill ſcattered againſt him, ſo that if he would cleer himſelf, be muſt be ever wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his own Vindication; this ſinck filling with ſuch ditch-water faſter then any one man can pumpe it out. In the mean time, what are they? or what do they deſerve? or for what end can all this be ſuppoſed to be done? but to villifie and render contemptible a man, that in his heart abominates all unjuſt wayes, which they know they are deeply engaged in.</p>
            <p>Then again, there are divers that make it their buſineſs about the Town, to cloſe with ſuch as they have any hopes will be flexible, and to adviſe them that they be cautious concerning Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> for knowing men ſay he is a Ieſuit, and 'ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> probable enough ſay they, for no body knows where he was born, or how he maintains himſelf; and that tis verily thought he was born in <hi>Spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n:</hi> Some ſix or ſeven men that have been thus Accoſted I know, and can produce, which ſhews that theſe things are not Caſual, but proceed from Deſign, and Pre-medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>How many are miſ-led into a belief hereof, and of the former Scandals already, I know not, but that no more may, and that ſuch as are, may be better informed: I hope without offence to any, I may give a brief and curſory Deſcription of Mr <hi>Walwyns</hi> Life and Diſpoſition, which is as follows;</p>
            <p>Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> was born at <hi>Newland</hi> in <hi>Worceſter-ſhire,</hi> of Mr <hi>Robert Walwyn</hi> Eſquire, a man of good Life and Repute in his Country, and of between three and four hundred pounds <hi>Annual</hi> Eſtate, that his Mother is ſtill living and was Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Doctor <hi>Weſtphaling</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hereford:</hi> his Brothers and Siſters are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in that Country; But he being a yonger Brother, was bound Apprentize in <hi>London,</hi> and ſerved out his Time with a Silk-man in Pater noſter-Row: A while after, he was made Free of the Merchant Adventurers Company, and hath ſince traded as Merchant about ſeventeen or eighteen yeers; dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng all which time, his aboads have bin known and certain, and his reſidence in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don conſtant, except two or three journeys into his owne Country, and one or two to the Army, before its firſt comming to London. That he was never over Sea in any Country whatſoever. That he has from the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117288:7"/>
profits of his Trade, maintained his Family in a middle and moderate, but contentful condition; having bin much waſted, but never gained one penny by theſe eight yeers diſtractions, nor ever deſired it; his only end, being that the Common-wealth might be ſo ſetled, that men might with comfort and alacrity ſet themſelves about their particular Callings and employments. That he is moſt ſtrictly abſtenious, and though of an open hand, and a large heart to his ability, yet did I never obſerve in any man ſo cautious and conſtant a Temperance.</p>
            <p>That I never obſerved in him the leaſt unſeemly geſture towards women, being a man noted by ſuch as intimately know him, for a moſt preciſe and exemplary modeſty, naturally expreſſing it ſelf (even at his yeers, which are almoſt fifty) at any obſcene word or behaviour, by a bluſh: which is an outward manifeſtation of the inward diſtaſt and reluctancy of the mind, againſt the evil of the preſent object. That he has lived 21 yeers and upward with one woman, and ſhe a truly good one; between whom I have obſerved ſo conſtant, ſo growing an affection, as that I have not known in my 8 yeers aboad with them, a haſty word paſs from one to the other: By her he has had almoſt twenty children; that before the Parliament, he informed himſelf of all the extravagancies and oppreſſions of the King; and out of diſlike thereof, and in hope that his Country ſhould by the endeavors of the Parliament be freed from them, he engaged with them; that he has continued ſo doing till this day; and though he hath bin much diſſwaded by his friends from croſſing the ſtream, and adviſed to ſwim in it; yet could he never bring his mind to it; the light of his own Conſcience guiding him otherwiſe. In this caſe, Charity (he thinks) ought not to begin at home, but at his Country; for though a mans ſelf may be allowed to be deerer then another, yet not then all. For the publike Liberties, he hath not onely conſtantly appeared, but reſcued moſt of them out of a heap of contrary Doctrines, and Politick concealments. And for Liberty of Conſcience, there is a book (the firſt that was brought to light upon that Subject, ſince theſe Troubles) doth ow much to his Induſtry: And though he is not ſo much concern'd in the point as other men, eſpecially his Adverſaries (he having never bin of any private Congregation) yet did he one of the firſt break the Ice in that point, ſince this Parliament, and to the utmoſt of his power, both by writing, and by frequent and very hazardable Addreſſes to Authority, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored both to evince the equity of the thing in it ſelf, and procure a Liberty for the Exerciſe thereof; as judging it a mans duty to move not onely for thoſe things that are of immediate concernment, but in thoſe alſo, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good and juſt, conduce to the more immediate benefit of his Brethren.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould reckon up all the good things he hath engaged in, I ſhould haply be too tireſome to the Reader. I will therefore ſay onely this, that I never knew him engage in any thing that could (except in a wreſted ſenſe) be ſaid to advantage a corrupt intereſt: He hath ſtudied the Peop es Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſo radically, and hath brought to light Principles ſo ſupportive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſo eſſential thereunto, that no other Deſigne but their good, can with any pretenſe be fixt upon him; except to the miſ-leading thoſe that know him not, or do not well k ow him. I wiſh with all my heart, the neceſſity of writing thus much, had not bin enforced upon me: For there is not any man I think, which loves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tireme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and the not being ſeen in this kind, more then I do.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117288:8"/>
            <p>Neither doth Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> take the leaſt pleaſure in applauſe, or the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good opinion of him, which no man hath more ſlighted; but expects his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe from Gods love to him (which certainly he will amply find, if not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hereafter;) from the calmneſs of his own Conſcience, and the reſpects of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> godly and ingenuous men; who not by hear-ſay, a caſual expreſſion, or ſlip of his tongue, do ſuppoſe they know him; but of ſuch as are neer and narrow obſervers of his Diſcourſes, Life, and Converſation.</p>
            <p>The other paſs many expreſſions of the lighteſt nature in the Book, that are not within the reach of my knowledge to diſprove. Some of them I have heard of from them, and that 5, or 6. yeers ago (which ſhews that the Timber for this Structure has bin long cut down, and that they have had time enough to ſhape it to their own purpoſes) I ſuppoſe they will, if there be further need, receive an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer by M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>For the particulars that concern Levelling mens Eſtates, &amp;c. M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> has given ſuch ample ſatisfaction, I conceive, in the Manifeſtation, which the Author too conceives to be principally his, that I wonder old expreſſions in beat of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes (who knows how long ago) drops from him (as who knows too how ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and miſtakingly ſince reported) ſhould be now urged upon him: But in order to a Deſign, what muſt not be done? But 'tis talks abroad, they can be proved; that is, that credible people have heard them, and will atteſt the ſame. To that I ſhall ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That M. <hi>Edwards</hi> had witneſſes for atteſtation of many ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he reported of pious and honeſt people, and yet how deſervedly were his ſlanders ſlighted, upon this ground, that men of different ſpirits do very familiarly hear with too open ears, and report with ſuch additions as their ſpleen and diſ-affection ſuggeſts againſt him they maligne? And as M. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> (whoſe hap it hath him to ſuffer much in this kind with M. <hi>Walwyn</hi>) well expreſſes himſelf in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to M. <hi>Edwards Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> p. 2. Sect. 3. <hi>There is no reaſonable m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n but will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and deduct, and that to a good proportion, from ſuch Reckonings and Accompts, which are drawn up and given into him by the hand of envie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That in many particulars urged upon M. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> the offence lies not in the things, but in the end for which they were done; which the Author takes upon him to judge; and does he not thereby (as M. <hi>Goodwin</hi> ſaies of M. <hi>Edwards</hi> in his <hi>Innocencies Tryumph,</hi> p. 3.) claim part or priviledge with God himſelf, in his Omniſcience or heart-ſearching, which is (as he goes on) to magnifie himſelf above all that is called man, and to ſet himſelf down in Gods chair.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of what credit pray is the teſtimony of an enemy in matters of obloquy and reproach, tending to the diſparagement of another; M. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> frequently tells you in his <hi>Hagiomaſtix,</hi> and his <hi>Cretenſes,</hi> or anſwer to M. <hi>Edwards</hi> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er one Treatiſe, eſpecially (I may add) when the memory is long charged therewith and when diſcontent, and new enmities do in the intervalls ariſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let it be conſidered how unlike it is to the way of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to have Eve-droppers, Agents, or Factors, to gather up, and furniſh themſelves with the ſins and infirmities of good men, who never took a report into their lips againſt any man, upon looſe or malicious ſuggeſtions, that pleaded the cauſe even of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultreſs, and ſtopt the mouths of her Accuſers: yet here hath our Author ranſackt all corners, ſifted every mans knowledge of M. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> and then taking onely the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or dregs of his life, hath with the unworthy addition of the ſlime of his brain,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117288:8"/>
made up a diſh for his own and his friends eating; and hopes that by the large commendations he gives of it, it will find acceptance among all other good people.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Author makes a difference between Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> and the reſt of his Fellow Priſoners, judging him to be the Principal, and they the Acceſſaries to the Chimetical Crimes, our Authors brains have fancied: to this I ſay. That they who do know, or do not conceal their knowledge of Lievt. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> muſt needs confeſs him to be a man the leaſt liable to be moulded or bowed by others, of any man in the world. Who biaz'd him I pray in all his ſufferings before in the Fleet, Oxford, Newgate, the Fleet again, the Tower, &amp;c? whoſe Counſel hath he taken in writing thoſe many Diſcoveries of bad mens wayes, but God and his own? But our Author writes not ſo much his knowledge as his gueſſe, and not ſo much his gueſs neither as his Deſign either to make difference between theſe Friends, or by laying the whole burden upon Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> to ſingle him our there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by for deſtruction. For Mr <hi>Prince,</hi> as he is a man of a ſingle heart, and lamb-like innocence; ſo is he far from pining his Faith upon another mans ſleive, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes himſelf guided in the preſent diſlikes he hath manifeſted, not by other mens diſcourſes, but by real and ſenſible ſufferings: By what his eyes ſee, his eares hear of the Peoples ſad and deplorable Condition: by apparent contradictions in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Engagements, by the benefit of Law taken away, and by abundance of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtances and experimental proofs of things, by which, and the ſenſe of his own duty, thereupon he is engaged, he ſayes, to ſhew himſelf as he doth. But I ſhall forbear to ſpeak further to this, ſince I hear they both intend to write ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Vindication of themſelves: For Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> in the ſuppoſition the world hath of him of being a Politick man; he is as much miſtakes as may be; Policy being taken in the worſt ſenſe, for an ability to do things good or bad, juſt or unjuſt for advantage, and the accompliſhment of an evil end. He is the moſt preciſely tyed as to good in the end, ſo in all the means in Order to that end, that I have often told him of the impoſſibillity of procuring that for the people his honeſt heart intended, againſt powers otherwaies reſolved; and here upon I have often perſwaded him to decline the Engaging as too difficult for him. To which he hath anſwered, That his thoughts did not ſo much inſiſt upon the ſucceſs, as his duty: the one he was bound to perform, the other was without him, not in his power; and therefore though he ſhould rejoyce at the good event of things, yet ſhould he not be diſmayed, when they fall out otherwayes, for that was at the good pleaſure of him, to whom he was to ſubmit.</p>
            <p>'Tis obſervable that ſome of thoſe that Subſcribed the Epiſtle Dedicatory, are his moſt deadly Enemies; and of thoſe, one hath very buſily ſpread abroad that moſt malicious ſuggeſtion of Mr <hi>Walwyns</hi> being a Ieſuit, although I ſuppoſe he himſelf know, the contrary: otherſome, namely the two laſt, have been very ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known unto him, or he of them; and yet they tell you too, that they <hi>therein Subſcribed their own experiences and obſervations of his general Courſe in all his wayes, as they are in the Book ſet forth.</hi> If this be the Courſe that muſt be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from theſe Church-men, whoſe fame or reputation can be ſafe? though never ſo carefully guarded by innocence, and a diligent eſchewing of evil? For as Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> hath ſuffer'd, ſo who may not? or who is not likely to ſuffer, that ſtands in the way at leaſt of their proſpect? Every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d muſt raile, and every heart muſt ſtoop to the Glory and Sanctity of theſe Saintly men, that have already ſuckt in large hopes of being Poſſeſſors of the Earth, and begin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtretch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117288:9"/>
and juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out other men as profane, worldly irreligions, and what Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe they pleaſe to defame them withal: Still muſt it be that new men riſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and tread in the ſame ſteps of reviling with their fore fathers. Was M. <hi>Walwyn</hi> a Traytor, Heretick, and Rebel in the Biſhops eſteem? Was he the Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap> Schiſmatick, Atheiſt, Anarchiſt, and what not thats bad and monſtrous, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his Conſcience could not ſtoop to them? And muſt the ſink of every mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lice be ſtill thrown upon him, and his render back preſt down with all the oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies that men of more copious and refin'd imaginations can invent and throw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: Muſt he ever be the man of infamy and diſgrace? whither then ſhall be appeal for relief and vindication, but at thy ſacred throne, almighty God, to whoſe Omniſcience the ſecret thoughts and inmoſt corners of every heart are like a Text in great Letters, viſible and tranſparent? Thy Majeſty haſt true and certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of every thing done and imagined in the world, thou kneweſt the innocence of thy ſervant <hi>Stephen,</hi> and the maliciouſneſs of the Iews that ſtoned him; the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of <hi>Tertullus</hi> in accuſing <hi>Paul,</hi> and of the forty Iews combin'd to deſtroy him. There is nothing at preſent that is hid from thee, no dark purpoſe or deſigne (though never ſo ſpeciouſly vaild over with good or Religious pretences, but is perſpicable by the eye of thy All-ſeeing Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>The frailty and dimneſſe of our ſight cannot diſtinguiſh between things that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and but ſeem to be, between Truth and Falſhood: inſomuch that this vain world frequently miſ-calls Good, Evil; and Evil Good: and upon confidence of this common frailty, bad men endowed with craft and vain policy, impoſe upon the weak and credulous what ſhape, and imaginations of things their wicked ende ſuggeſt unto them Foraſmuch as therefore O Lord, thou art the, protectour of all the Innocent, and detector of the falſe accuſers, give ſome real manifeſtation to the World, both of the one and of the other; open the breaſts of Mr <hi>Walwyn</hi> and his Accuſers: Let their thoughts be manifeſt, the ſecret purpoſes and deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their hearts written as in their fore-heads; that ſo thy Name may have the glory in a plain and viſible diſcovery of them both, and the innocence of the one ſhine more bright by this fiery Tryal it is now undergoing; and the ſecret ends and contrivances of the other be no longer conceal'd under the painted garment of zeal towards thee and thy Word, which thou knoweſt O God, is by many of them put on purpoſely to enable them to deſtroy innocent men, and to perſecute thy Chriſt in his Members.</p>
            <p>But if O Lord thou haſt decreed that bad men ſhall run on in the courſe of their wickedneſſe, till their meaſure be full, and wilt ſuffer them to be chaſtizing inſtruments in thy band, for the many frailties and ſinnes of thy ſervants, thy will be done, only ſupport us we beſeech thee with the ſtrength of thy inward conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with patience to drink of that Cup thou haſt provided for thy ſervants, and to ſubmit all we are or have, to thy hand, thy wiſdom, thy will, our Lord, our God, our Father.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 2 <hi>line</hi> 13 <hi>for</hi> uſually, <hi>read</hi> unjuſtly. <hi>l.</hi> 37 <hi>for</hi> coupled <hi>r</hi> centupled. <hi>l.</hi> 39. <hi>for</hi> changing <hi>r</hi> changes. <hi>l</hi> 49 <hi>for</hi> luſt of, <hi>r</hi> by the laſt, all that are rich. <hi>p.</hi> 3 <hi>l</hi> 11 <hi>for</hi> lines <hi>r</hi> lives. <hi>p.</hi> 4 <hi>l</hi> 12 <hi>for</hi> ſeverally <hi>r</hi> generally. <hi>p.</hi> 7 <hi>l</hi> 6 <hi>for</hi> rule Scripture, <hi>r</hi> rule of Scripture.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
